Good evening.
مساء الخير.
My journey to this stage
رحلتي إلى هذا المسرح
began when I came to America
بدأت حين أتيت إلى أمريكا
at the age of 17.
في عمر الـ17 .
You see, I'm one of the 84 million Americans
ترون، أنا واحدة من 84 مليون أمريكي
who are immigrants
الذين هم مهاجرون
or children of immigrants.
أو أطفال المهاجرون.
Each of us has a dream when we come here,
كل واحد منا لديه حلم عندما أتى إلى هنا
a dream that usually has to be rewritten
حلم، في بعض الأوقات يجب علينا صياغته مجدداَ
and always has to be repurposed.
ودائما بحاجة لإعادة توظيفه
I was one of the lucky ones.
كنت أحد المحظوظين.
My revised dream led me to the work I do today:
حلمي المُعدل قادني إلى عملي اليوم:
training immigrants to run for public office
تدريب المهاجرين ليشغلو مناصب عامة
and leading a movement for inclusive democracy.
وقيادة حركة من أجل الديموقراطية الشاملة.
But I don't want you to think it was a cakewalk,
لكن لا تظنوا بأن الأمر أشبه بنزهة
that America opened its arms wide and welcomed me.
وبأن أمريكا رحبت بي وفتحت ذراعيها لي .
It's still not doing that.
إنها لا تزال لا تفعل ذلك.
And I've learned a few lessons along the way
ولقد تعلمت العديد من الدروس خلال مسيرتي
that I wanted to share with you,
والتي اردت أن أشاركها معكم،
because I think that together
لأنني أعتقد ،معاً
we can make American democracy
سنجعل ديموقراطية أمريكا
better and stronger.
أفضل وأقوى.
I was born in India,
لقد وُلدتُ في الهند،
the world's largest democracy,
أكبر ديموقراطية عالمية،
and when I was four,
وحين كنت في الرابعة،
my family moved to Belize,
انتقلت عائلتي إلى بيليز،
the world's smallest democracy perhaps.
ربما أصغر ديموقراطية في العالم.
And at the age of 17,
وفي عمر الـ17
I moved to the United States,
انتقلت للولايات المتحدة،
the world's greatest democracy.
أعظم ديموقراطية في العالم.
I came because I wanted to study English literature.
أتيت لأنني رغبت في دراسة الأدب الانكليزي.
You see, as a child, I buried my nose in books,
كما ترون ، كطفلة دفنت نفسي في الكتب،
and I thought, why not make a living doing that as an adult?
وفكرت لماذا لا أكسب عيشي خلال فعل هذا عندما أكبر؟
But after I graduated from college
ولكن بعد أن تخرجت من الجامعة
and got a graduate degree,
وحصلت على شهادة التخرج،
I found myself moving from one less ideal job to another.
وجدت نفسي انتقل من عمل أقل مثالية إلى آخر.
Maybe it was the optimism that I had about America
ربما النظرة التفاؤلية التي كانت لدي عن أمريكا
that made me take a while to understand
جعلتني أفكر أكثر لاستوعب
that things were not going to change.
بأن الأمور لن تتغيير.
The door that I thought was open
الباب الذي خلته مفتوحاً
was actually just slightly ajar --
بالحقيقة كان موارباً قليلاً--
this door of America
هذا الباب الأمريكي
that would open wide if you had the right name,
الذي سيُفتح على مصراعيه إذا كنت تملك الاسم المناسب،
the right skin color,
لون البشرة المناسب،
the right networks,
الصلات المناسبة،
but could just slam in your face
ولكن سيصفع بوجهك
if you had the wrong religion,
إذا كنت من الدين الخطأ،
the wrong immigration status,
وضع الهجرة الخطأ،
the wrong skin color.
لون البشرة الخطأ.
And I just couldn't accept that.
ولم استطع أن أتقبل ذلك.
So I started a career as a social entrepreneur,
لهذا بدأت مهنتي كأحد الرواد الاجتماعيين،
starting an organization for young people like myself --
بدايةً بمؤسسة للشباب مثلي--
I was young at the time that I started it --
كنت شابة في ذلك الوقت ،حين بدأت
who traced their heritage to the Indian subcontinent.
مؤسسة للشباب الذين يعود إرثهم لشبه القارة الهندية.
In that work, I became and advocate for South Asians and other immigrants.
في ذلك العمل، أصبحت مستشارة للشباب الاسيوين ومهاجرين آخرين.
I lobbied members of Congress on policy issues.
شكلت قوى ضاغطة على أعضاء من الكونغرس بشأن قضايا السياسة العامة.
I volunteered on election day to do exit polling.
تطوعت في يوم الانتخاب للانتهاء من الاقتراع.
But I couldn't vote, and I couldn't run for office.
لكن لم يمكنني التصويت، ولا الترشح لمنصب عام.
So in 2000, when it was announced
لهذا في عام 2000 عندما تم الاعلان
that the citizenship application fee was going to more than double
بأن رسوم طلب الجنسية ستتضاعف
from 95 dollars to 225 dollars,
من 95 دولار إلى 225 دولار،
I decided it was time to apply before I could no longer afford it.
قررت بأنه حان الوقت لأسجل قبل أن لا استطيع تحمل تكلفة الأمر.
I filled out a long application,
ملأت استمارة طلب طويلة،
answering questions about my current and my past affiliations.
مجيبة عن اسئلة حول انتماءاتي الحالية والماضية.
And once the application was submitted,
وبمجرد تقديم الطلب،
there were fingerprints to be taken,
كان هناك أخذ بصمات،
a test to study for,
فحص لدراسة الحالة،
endless hours of waiting in line.
وساعات غير معدودة من الانتظار.
You might call it extreme vetting.
يمكن أن نسميه تدقيق شديد.
And then in December of 2000,
ومن ثم في ديسمبر
I joined hundreds of other immigrants
انضممت إلى المئات من المهاجرين
in a hall in Brooklyn
في قاعة في بروكلين
where we pledged our loyalty
حيث تعهدنا بولائنا
to a country that we had long considered home.
لبلد لطالما اعتبرناه وطن.
My journey from international student to American citizen took 16 years,
رحلتي من طالبة دولية إلى مواطنة أمريكية أخذت 16 عاماً
a short timeline when you compare it to other immigrant stories.
هذا وقت قصير مقارنةً بقصص المهاجرين الاخرى.
And soon after I had taken that formal step
وبعد فترة قصيرة من أخذي لهذه الخطوة الرسمية
to becoming an American,
لأصبح أمريكية،
the attacks of September 11, 2001,
هجمات الحادي عشر من سبتمبر
changed the immigration landscape for decades to come.
غيرت مشهد الهجرة لعقود قادمة.
My city, New York City,
مدينتي ، مدينة نيويورك
was reeling and healing,
كانت تترنح وتُشفى،
and in the midst of it,
وفي خضم ذلك،
we were in an election cycle.
كنا في دائرة الانتخاب.
Two things happened
حصل شيئان
as we coped with loss and recovery in New York City.
عندما تعاملنا مع الخسارة والتعافي في مدينة نيويورك.
Voters elected Michael Bloomberg mayor of New York City.
الناخبين صوّتوا لـ مايكل بلومبيرغ عمدةً لمدينة نيويورك.
We also adopted by ballot referendum
اعتمدنا أيضا عن طريق استفتاء الاقتراع
the Office of Immigrant Affairs for the City of New York.
مكتب شؤون المهاجرين في مدينة نيويورك.
Five months after that election,
بعد الانتخاب بخمسة أشهر،
the newly elected mayor
العمدة المنتخب حديثاً
appointed me the first Commissioner of Immigrant Affairs
عينني المفوضة الأولى لشؤون المهاجرين
for this newly established office.
للمكتب الذي أُنشئ حديثاً.
I want you to come back to that time.
أريد منكم أن تعودوا إلى وقت كنت فيه
I was a young immigrant woman from Belize.
فتاة صغيرة مهاجرة من بيليز.
I had basically floundered in various jobs in America
كنت قد تعثرت بشكل أساسي بوظائف عديدة في امريكا
before I started a community-based organization
قبل أن أبدأ منظمة مجتمعية
in a church basement in Queens.
في قبو كنيسة في كوينز.
The attacks of September 11 sent shock waves through my community.
أرسلت هجمات 11 سبتمبر موجات صدمة عبر مجتمعي.
People who were members of my family, young people I had worked with,
أشخاص كانوا أفراد في عائلتي، أشخاص يافعين عملت معهم،
were experiencing harassment
تعرضوا لاعتداءات
at schools, at workplaces and in airports.
في المدارس، في أماكن العمل وفي المطارات.
And now I was going to represent their concerns
والآن سأُمثل مخاوفهم
in government.
في الحكومة.
No job felt more perfect for me.
لا عمل أفضل من هذا بالنسبة لي.
And here are two things I learned when I became Commissioner.
وهنالك شيئان تعلمتهما عندما أصبحت مفوضة.
First, well-meaning New Yorkers
أولاً، حسن نية سكان نيويورك
who were in city government holding government positions
الذين كانوا في حكومة المدينة يشغلون مناصب حكومية
had no idea how scared immigrants were
الذين لا يملكون أي فكرة كم كان خوف المهاجرين
of law enforcement.
من المسؤولين القانونيين
Most of us don't really know the difference, do we,
أغلبنا لا يعرف الفرق، هل نعرف
between a sheriff and local police and the FBI.
الفرق بين الشريف وشرطي محلي وFBI.
And most of us, when we see someone in uniform
ومعظمنا حين نرى شخص ما في زي رسمي
going through our neighborhoods
يتجول في أحيائنا
feel curiosity, if not concern.
نشعر بالفضول إن لم يكن القلق.
So if you're an undocumented parent,
لهذا إذا كنتم والدين ولا تحملوا وثائق رسمية
every day when you say goodbye to your child,
كل يوم عندما تقولوا وداعا لطفلك
send them off to school and go to work,
وترسلوهم إلى المدرسة وتذهبوا إلى العمل
you don't know what the chances are
لا تعلمون ماهي الفرص
that you're going to see them at the end of the day.
بأنكم ستروهم في نهاية اليوم.
Because a raid at your workplace,
بسبب مداهمة على مكان عملك،
a chance encounter with local police
واحتمال مصادفة شرطي محلي
could change the course of your life forever.
بإمكانها أن تغير مجرى حياتك للأبد.
The second thing I learned is that when people like me,
الشيء الثاني الذي تعلمته، هو عندما يكون هنالك أشخاص مثلي
who understood that fear,
يعرفون هذا الخوف،
who had learned a new language, who had navigated new systems,
الذين تعلموا لغة جديدة ، الذين أبحروا في أنظمة جديدة،
when people like us were sitting at the table,
عندما يجلس أشخاص مثلنا إلى الطاولة
we advocated for our communities' needs in a way that no one else could or would.
نحن ندافع عن احتياجات مجتمعنا بطريقة لا يمكن لأحد أن يفعلها أو يريد ذلك
I understood what that feeling of fear was like.
أنا أفهم ماذا يشبه هذا الخوف.
People in my family were experiencing it.
أشخاص في عائلتي اختبروه.
Young people I had worked with were being harassed,
أشخاص يافعين عملت معهم تعرضوا لمضايقات
not just by classmates,
ليس فقط من الزملاء،
but also by their teachers.
ولكن أيضا من أساتذتهم.
My husband, then boyfriend,
زوجي وثم صديقي
thought twice before he put a backpack on or grew a beard
فكر مرتان قبل أن يحمل حقيبة ظهر أو يربي لحية
because he traveled so much.
لأنه يسافر كثيراً.
What I learned in 2001 was that my vote mattered
الذي تعلمته في 2001 ،بأن صوتي مهم
but that my voice and vantage point also mattered.
لكن صوتي ووجهة نظري أيضا مهمان.
And it's these three things --
وهناك ثلاثة أشياء:
immigrants' votes, voices and vantage points --
تصويت المهاجرين، الأصوات ووجهات النظر
that I think can help make our democracy stronger.
التي أعتقد بإمكانها أن تساعد بتعزيز الديموقراطية
We actually have the power
نحن نملك القوة
to change the outcome of elections,
لنغير نتائج الانتخابات،
to introduce new issues into the policy debate
لنقدم قضايا جديدة للسياسة العامة
and to change the face of the pale, male, stale leadership
ولنغير وجه القيادة الشاحب والذكوري والذي لا معنى له
that we have in our country today.
الذي نملكه اليوم في بلدنا.
So how do we do that?
إذاً كيف سنفعل هذا؟
Well, let's talk first about votes.
حسناً، لنتكلم أولاً عن الأصوات.
It will come as no surprise to you
إنه لن يفاجئكم
that the majority of voters in America are white.
أن غالبية الناخبين في أمريكا بيض
But it might surprise you to know
ولكن سيفاجئكم بأن تعلموا
that one in three voters are black, Latino or Asian.
بأن هناك واحد من ثلاث ناخبين أسود أو لاتيني أو آسيوي.
But here's the thing:
وهنا الأمر
it doesn't just matter who can vote, it matters who does vote.
إنه لا يهم من يمكنه التصويت المهم من يصوّت بالفعل.
So in 2012, half of the Latino and Asian-American voters
لهذا في عام 2012 ، نصف الناخبين اللاتينين والاسيوامريكين
did not vote.
لم يصوتوا.
And these votes matter not just in presidential elections.
وهذا الأصوات مهمة ليس في الانتخابات الرئاسية وحسب
They matter in local and state elections.
بل أيضاً في الانتخابات المحلية والولاية.
In 2015, Lan Diep,
في 2015 لان ديب
the eldest son of political refugees from Vietnam,
الابن الأكبر لمهاجر سياسي من فيتنام
ran for a seat in the San Jose City Council.
ترشح لمقعد في مجلس مدينة سان خوسيه.
He lost that election by 13 votes.
هو خسر ذلك الاقتراع ب13 صوت
This year, he dusted off those campaign shoes
هذه السنة نفض غبار الهزيمة عن حملته
and went back to run for that seat,
وترشح مرة أخرى لذلك المقعد
and this time he won, by 12 votes.
وهذه المرة ربح بفارق 12 صوت.
Every one of our votes matters.
كل صوت من أصواتنا مهم.
And when people like Lan are sitting at the policy table,
وعندما يجلس أشخاص كـ لان إلى طاولة السياسة
they can make a difference.
بإمكانهم إن يصنعوا الفرق.
We need those voices.
نحن بحاجة لهذه الأصوات .
We need those voices
نحن بحاجة هذه الأصوات
in part because American leadership
ويرجع ذلك لأن القيادة الأمريكية
does not look like America's residents.
لا تشبه المقيمين الأمريكيين.
There are over 500,000 local and state offices in America.
هناك أكثر من 500 ألف مكتب ولاية ومحلي في أمريكا .
Fewer than 2 percent of those offices are held by Asian-Americans or Latinos,
أقل من 2% من هذه المكاتب مرؤوسة من قبل آسيوين ولاتينين،
the two largest immigrant groups in our country.
أكبر جماعتين من المهاجرين في بلادنا.
In the city of Yakima, Washington,
في مدينة ياكيما، واشنطن
where 49 percent of the population is Latino,
حيث 49 بالمئة من تعداد السكان هم لاتينيون،
there has never been a Latino on the city council until this year.
لم يكن هناك لاتيني في مجلس المدينة لحد هذه السنة.
Three newly elected Latinas joined the Yakima City Council in 2016.
ثلاث لاتينين منتخبين حديثاً انضموا لمجلس مدينة ياكيما في 2016.
One of them is Carmen Méndez.
أحدهم هي كاميرون مينديز.
She is a first-generation college student.
هي أحد أول جيل متخرج من الكلية.
She grew up partly in Colima, Mexico,
ترعرعت في كوليما ، مكسيك جزء من حياتها
and partly in Yakima, Washington.
والجزء الاخر في ياكيما ،واشنطن.
She's a single mother, a community advocate.
هي أم عزباء ، محامية مجتمع.
Her voice on the Yakima City Council
صوتها في مجلس مدينة ياكيما
is advocating on behalf of the Latino community
هو صوت مدافع عن المجتمع اللاتيني
and of all Yakima residents.
وعن كل سكان ياكيما.
And she's a role model for her daughter
هي قدوة لطفلتها
and other Latinas.
وللـ اللاتينين الاخرين.
But the third most untapped resource in American democracy
ولكن ثالث أكبر الموارد الغير مستغلة في الديموقراطية الامريكية
is the vantage point that immigrants bring.
هي وجهة نظر التي يجلبها المهاجرون .
We have fought to be here.
لقد قاتلنا لنكون هنا .
We have come for economic and educational opportunity.
لقد أتينا لفرصة اقتصادية وتعليمية .
We have come for political and religious freedom.
أتينا من أجل الحرية السياسية والدينية.
We have come in the pursuit of love.
أتينا بحثاً عن الحب.
That dedication,
هذا التفاني،
that commitment to America
الملتزمون به لأمريكا
we also bring to public service.
سنجلبه أيضا للخدمات العامة.
People like Athena Salman,
أُناس كـ أثينا سلمان،
who just last week won the primary
التي فازت مؤخراً
for a seat in the Arizona State House.
بالحصول على مقعد في مجلس ولاية اريزونا.
Athena's father grew up in the West Bank
والد أثنيا تربى في الضفة الغربية
and moved to Chicago,
وانتقل إلى شيكاغو،
where he met her mother.
حيث التقى بوالدتها.
Her mother is part Italian,
والدتها جزء ايطالي
part Mexican and part German.
جزء مكسيكي وجزء ألماني.
Together they moved to Arizona and built a life.
سوياً انتقلوا إلى اريزونا ليُأسسوا حياة.
Athena, when she gets to the statehouse,
أثينا وصلت إلى مجلس الولاية،
is going to fight for things like education funding
وستقاتل لأشياء كتمويل التعليم
that will help give families like hers a leg up
الذي سيساعد عائلات كعائلتها في الدعم
so they can achieve the financial stability
ليحققوا الاستقرار المالي
that we all are looking for.
الذي نبحث عنه جميعاً.
Immigrants' votes, voices and vantage points
أصوات المهاجرين، أصوات ووجهات نظر
are what we all need to work to include in American democracy.
هذا كل مانحتاجه للعمل بأن نكون جزءاً من ديموقراطية أمريكا.
It's not just my work. It's also yours.
هذا ليس عملي وحسب بل عملكم أيضاً.
And it's not going to be easy.
ولن يكون سهلاً.
We never know
لا نعلم أبداً،
what putting a new factor into an equation will do.
ما يمكن أن يفعله وضع عنصر جديد في المعادلة.
And it's a little scary.
وهذا مخيف قليلاً،
You're scared that I'm going to take away your place at the table,
أنتم خائفون بأني سآخذ مكانكم على الطاولة
and I'm scared that I'm never going to get a place at the table.
وأنا خائفة بأني لن أحصل على مكان في الطاولة.
And we're all scared
جميعنا خائفون
that we're going to lose this country that we know and love.
بأننا سنخسر هذا البلد الذي نعرف ونحب.
I'm scared you're going to take it away from me,
أنا خائفة بأنكم ستأخدوه مني،
and you're scared I'm going to take it away from you.
أنتم خائفون بأني سآخذه منكم.
Look, it's been a rough election year,
انظروا لقد كانت سنة انتخابات عصيبة،
a reminder that people with my immigration history
تذكرة بأن الناس الذين مثل تاريخ هجرتي
could be removed at the whim of a leader.
يمكن أن يُزالو بنزوة زعيم.
But I have fought to be in this country
لكني قاتلت لأكون في هذا البلد
and I continue to do so every day.
وأتابع القتال كل يوم.
So my optimism never wavers,
لذا تفائلي لم يتزعزع،
because I know that there are millions of immigrants just like me,
لأني أعلم بأن هناك ملايين المهاجرين مثلي،
in front of me, behind me and all around me.
أمامي، خلفي وحولي.
It's our country, too.
هذا بلدنا أيضاً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)